我们要看的最后一个术语是“C”，它代表科里奥利和
The last term we're going to look at is the term 'C' and it represents the Coriolis and
存在于串行链接机器人操纵器内的向心扭矩。它通常被称为
Centripetal torques that exists within a serial link robot manipulator. It's often called
速度项是因为C矩阵乘以矢量Q点，即关节速度的矢量。
the velocity term because the C matrix multiplies the vector Q dot, the vector of joint velocities.
这是由于旋转关节引起的陀螺效应引起的扭矩
This is the torque that is due to gyroscopic effects due to rotating joints within the
机器人机械手。实际上有两种效果由矩阵C和C建模
robot manipulator. There are actually two effects that are modelled by the matrix C and
这是以法国科学家，数学家科里奥利（Coriolis）命名的科里奥利效应
it's the Coriolis effect which is named after the French scientist, mathematician Coriolis
他在理解旋转参考系中发生的事情方面做了很多工作
and he did a lot of work on understanding what goes on in rotating reference frames
并且由矩阵C表示的另一个力是向心力矩。
and the other force represented by the matrix C are centripetal torques.
我们再一次用象征性地表示我们的两个链接机器人，这次我们要去
Once again we have our two link robot represented symbolically and this time we're going to
研究科里奥利和向心力矩。这是使用名为coriolis的方法完成的
investigate the Coriolis and centripetal torques. And that's done using the method called coriolis
对它的论证是关节角度，它们是关节角度和联合速度;Q1D和Q2D。
and the arguments to that are the joint angles, there they are and the joint velocities; Q1D and Q2D.
需要一点时间来计算，这是科里奥利和向心矩阵。
It takes a moment to compute and this is the Coriolis and centripetal matrix.
它是一个2x2矩阵，我们再次看到它包含了许多运动和动态
It's a 2 x 2 matrix and we can see, once again that it comprises a number of kinematic and dynamic
机器人的参数，我们也可以看到它是配置的一个功能
parameters of a robot and we can also see that it's a function of the configuration
机器人有趣的是，在这种情况下，它只是Q2的一个功能。
of a robot. Interestingly, in this case it’s only a function of Q2.
对于一个简单的2连杆机器人操纵器，C矩阵看起来像这样。我们可以
For a simple 2 link robot manipulator, the C matrix looks something like this. We can
看到元素是关节角度的函数，在这种情况下只是一个关节
see that the elements are a function of the joint angle, in this case just a single joint
角度。关节2角度Q2以及两个关节Q1点和Q2点的速度。
angle. Joint 2 angle Q2 and also the velocities of the two joints Q1 dot and Q2 dot.
现在，由于科里奥利和向心效应的扭矩可以通过乘以得出
Now the torque, due to the Coriolis and centripetal effects can be derived by multiplying the
矩阵C由关节速度的向量组成，如果我们扩展出来，我们就有了表达式
matrix C by the vector of joint velocities and if we expand that out, we have the expression
科林奥利和向心谈判在联合1和联合2上行事。
for the Coriolis and centripetal talks acting on Joint 1 and acting on Joint 2.
让我们考虑联合1没有移动的情况，即Q1点等于零
Let's consider the case where Joint 1 is not moving that’s Q1 dot is equal to zero but
让我们说联合2正在移动，所以Q2点不等于零。然后虽然这个词
let's say that Joint 2 is moving so Q2 dot is not equal to zero. Then although this term
这里等于零。这个术语在这里是有限的，即第2关节的运动
here is equal to zero. This term here will be finite, that is the motion of Joint 2 at
恒定速度将在关节1上产生扭矩，而这又是一种扭矩
constant velocity is going to induce a torque on Joint 1 and that's again something that
联合1运动控制器将不得不反对，必须反对
the Joint 1 motion controller is going to have to fight against, going to have to oppose
为了保持关节1静止。
in order to keep Joint 1 stationary.
同样地，我们可以看到，对于关节1，关节1的恒定速度运动正在进行
And similarly we can see that for Joint 2 constant velocity motion of Joint 1 is going
引起关节2的科里奥利和向心效应。现在，如果我们看一下这些术语，
to induce a Coriolis and centripetal effect on Joint 2. Now if we look at these terms,
我们可以看到它们中的一些是特定关节速度平方和的函数
we can see that some of them are a function of a particular joint velocity squared and
这些是向心式的谈话，其中一些是一个联合速度倍增的产物
these are the centripetal talks and some of them are a product of one joint velocity multiplied
通过不同的关节速度，这些是科里奥利术语。所以这个矩阵C已经有了
by a different joint velocity and these are the Coriolis terms. So this matrix C has got
一些术语是不同关节的速度的产物，一些是关节速度
some terms which are the products of velocities of different joints and some are joint velocity
平方，科里奥利和向心效应。
squared, Coriolis and centripetal effects.